<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<title>Sourabh Bajaj</title>
<link href="http://sourabhbajaj.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
<link href="http://sourabhbajaj.com"/>
<updated>2019-08-04T15:51:28-05:00</updated>
<id>http://sourabhbajaj.com</id>


<entry>
  <title>Introduction to My Research</title>
  <link href="http://sourabhbajaj.com/blog/2019/08/03/introduction-to-my-research/"/>
  
  <updated>2019-08-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <id>/blog/2019/08/03/introduction-to-my-research</id>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone, this is my first blog post where I will give a higher
level overview of my PhD research.  Several of my side projects stem
from curiousities based off my research, so I think it makes sense to
have this post as a point of reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-storage-devices&quot;&gt;Energy Storage Devices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Fluid Interface Reactions, Structure, and Transport (FIRST)
Center, we are focused on understanding the transport of ions for
energy-storage applications.  Currently, energy storage devices are
all limited in some for or another.  Batteries for example, exhibit
high energy density but low power density.  If you think about
batteries in the sense of electric vehicles, high energy density
allows for them to travel longer distances in between charges.  Lower
power density however means that an electric vehicle requires longer
time to charge.  Supercapacitors on the other hand, exhibit high power
density and low energy density.  This makes supercapacitors more
suitable for applications such as regenerative braking, where energy
needs to be delivered at higher rates.  This can be viewed in the
Ragone plot below (courtesy of Matt Thompson).  Overall, the ultimate goal is
to develop energy-storage devices that have both high energy and power
density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog/aug19/ragone.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ragone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the FIRST Center, we have approached this problem from the side of
supercapacitors.  I won’t go into too much detail here, but
supercapacitors store energy through the adsorption of ions on
surfaces of electrodes.  Unlike batteries, there are no chemical
reactions so transport is the rate-limiting process in supercapacitor
energy storage.  In other words, electrolytes with faster diffusion
and conductivity can enhance the power density of a supercapacitor.
Now to pivot slightly to energy density.  Energy density is governed
by the following equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;E = \frac{1}{2}CV^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where E is energy density, C is capacitance and V is the voltage.  As
you can see, if we operate these devices at higher voltages, we can
quadratically improve the energy density.  This is where ionic liquids
come into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ionic-liquids&quot;&gt;Ionic Liquids&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ionic liquids are salts that are liquid at ambient conditions.  The
reason ionic liquids are attractive electrolytes for energy storage is
that they have high operational voltage windows.  Going back to the
quadratic increase in energy density, the ability for ionic liquids to
withstand higher voltages means we can achieve this quadratic
increase.  The major downside of ionic liquids is that they exhibit
slow transport properties, which can decrease the power density
performance.  To solve this problem, ionic liquids can be solvated
with organic solvents to improve ion transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;molecular-dynamics&quot;&gt;Molecular Dynamics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To study ionic liquids, I use molecular dynamics (MD) simulations.  I
will only provide a higher level overview, but MD simulations
integrate over Newton’s equations of motion over time to track the
forces and positions of molecules.  When studying electrolytes, we
primarily use MD simulations to study the structure and transport.
During my three years as a graduate student, I’ve spent the majority
of my time screening over 400 solvated ionic liquids with various
solvents and concentrations.  If you’re interested, you can read more
about this study here.  We are continuing to study these solutions,
and have additional papers in preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a very brief overview of what I’ve been working on for the
last three years, but hopefully it’s enough to understand the
motivation for several side projects I’ve been working on.  In
addition to ionic liquids, we are also beginning to use MD simulations
to study MXenes, which are novel 2D titanium carbides/nitrides.  If
you have any questions, feel free to reach out to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>


</feed>
